# Jie JW Wu

\* https://jie-jw-wu.github.io/ \* (425) 301-0801 \* jiewu@gwu.edu

# **RESEARCH INTEREST**

I work in the intersection of AI and Software Engineering (SE). In the era of Big Data and Generative AI, I develop new approaches to simplify the complicated, time-consuming and sometimes tedious process of software development and decision-making in a more systematic, formalized way.

Led by this goal, my research interests are a) <u>AI4SE</u> and b) <u>SE4AI</u> within the context of Large Language Models (LLM), Machine Learning (ML), and Data as a component to assist, systematize and automate the decision-making of software developers and other roles within the enterprises. My previous experiences include but are not limited to the following areas:

- LLM-based approach for software engineering tasks
- Software development process for ML-enabled systems
- Continuous data-driven software engineering (online and offline A/B testing)
- Automated tooling to assist developers or end users
- Search-based software engineering (evolutionary algorithms)
- Data-driven decision-making (multi-criteria decision-making)
- Recommender system (evaluation, candidate generation, ranking)

# **EDUCATION**

# GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Ph.D. in Systems Engineering, Dept. of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering, May 2023 Dissertation: Towards Formalizing Data-Driven Decision-Making from Big Data: A Systematic Multi-Criteria Decision-Making Approach in Online Controlled Experiments *GPA*: 3.93/4.0

# SHANGHAI JIAO TONG UNIVERSITY

M.S., Dept. of Computer Science, Apr 2015 (major GPA: 3.94/4.0) B.S., <u>ACM Honored Class</u>, Dept. of Computer Science, Jun 2012

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# **SELF-EMPLOYMENT**

Independent Researcher, Jul 2023 – Present

• Working on research papers and prototypes toward "AI-Driven development".

# GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Ph.D. Research Study, Aug 2019 - May 2023

Advisor: Prof. Thomas Mazzuchi, Prof. Shahram Sarkani

<u>Dept. of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering, School of Engineering and Applied Science</u> (SEAS)

• Conducted research on a launch decision making framework for online controlled experiments (A/B testing) using a systematic multi-criteria decision-making (MCDM) approach. It's the first attempt to formalize and model the empirical decision-making process from A/B test results using MCDM. Published the approach as first author in "Information and Software Technology".

- Conducted research on developing techniques based on multi-criteria evolutionary algorithms (MOEA) for automating A/B testing. Published the approach as first author in "Journal of Systems & Software".
- Developed the research strategy  $SD^4$  "Systematic Data-Driven Decision-Making from Big Data Technologies" that indicates research opportunities to better formalize, automate and assist the empirical decision-making process in the software development and management process.

# **GOOGLE RESEARCH**

Research Intern, Jun 2014 - Oct 2014

Mentor: Dr. Hui Fang

Project: Deep Learning for Image Enhancement,

- Trained a deep learning model that simulate multiple filter effects for an input image.
- Designed and implemented a tool that decomposes the image into multiple image bases using trained model, then compose multiple filter effects.
- Implemented a GUI application that shows instant interpolated filter effects when user adjusts the parameter bar.

#### MICROSOFT RESEARCH ASIA

Research Intern, Multimedia Search & Mining Group, Jul 2013 – May 2014

Project: Smart Ink

Advisor: Dr. Changhu Wang, Prof. Liqing Zhang

- Implemented an Add-In on Microsoft Visio, which recognizes and converts hand-drawn shapes into formal shapes interactively, detects user's correction or editing on shapes, greatly facilitating the flowchart production.
- Pushed the limit of hand-drawn flowchart/diagram recognition from 75.0% to 81.9% on a public benchmark dataset, with state-of-the-art speed and memory cost (0.56s per image).
- Implemented a module that rapidly recognizes shapes/flowcharts/diagrams from an image taken by cell phone, then convert them into a ppt file with recognized formal shapes.
- As the only developer and experiment conductor for SmartInk demonstrated at Microsoft TechFest, Redmond. Published SmartInk techniques as first author in top-tier AI conferences (AAAI, IJCAI).

# SHANGHAI JIAO TONG UNIVERSITY

Undergraduate & M.S. Research Study, Jan 2012 – Jul 2013

Advisor: Prof. Liqing Zhang

Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering

• Conducted research on leveraging Gestalt Principles for the problem of salient region detection. Published the work as first author in ICIP conference.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **SNAP INC., Seattle, WA**

Software Engineer, Feb 2017 – Jul 2023

Teams: Core Growth ML, User & Friend, Friend Recommendation, Friending Infrastructure (Identity)

- Led several projects on evaluating the recall of friend recommendations reliably and comprehensively to guide the planning and prioritization of Friending team.
- Led several projects on new privacy algorithms to expand friend suggestion inventory during registration.
- Designed, and launched several scalable systems and algorithms that generate ~5 billion of friend suggestions every day, leading to ~10 million daily friend additions (~40% increase) from recommendation system. The types of friend suggestions of my system include 1) variants of Friends-of-Friends suggestions, 2) group-chat suggestions ("in a group with you"), 3) contact book related suggestions, 4) new user suggestions, etc.

- Designed and implemented algorithms to expand the Friends-of-Friends friend suggestion inventory to generate more suggestions, while still keeping users' friends list private. A US patent is applied for this algorithm titled "Additive Friend Suggestion System".
- Optimized a large-scale friend-link aggregation data pipeline that saved the infrastructure cost by 0.8 million / year (top 3 cost saving in the company-wide cost saving camp).

# MICROSOFT CORPORATION, Redmond, WA

Software Engineer, OneNote Canvas & Ink Team, Oct 2015 – Feb 2017

Project: OneNote Canvas

- Implemented and launched several features on OneNote Canvas including *ink selection enhancement, canvas accessibility*.
- Co-created and shipped a new algorithm for selecting a group of strokes intuitively in OneNote app. A US patent is granted for our new algorithm titled "Intuitive Selection of a Digital Stroke Grouping".

# **PUBLICATIONS**

- Wu, Jie JW. Can Offline A/B Testing Be Automated for Data-Driven Requirement Engineering? (Under Review)
- Wu, Jie JW. Does Asking Clarifying Questions Increases Confidence in Generated Code? On the Communication Skills of Large Language Models. Arxiv. (Under Review)
- Wu, Jie JW. Application of Systems Engineering Process in ML-Enabled Systems. Arxiv. (Under Review)
- Wu, Jie JW, Thomas A. Mazzuchi, Shahram Sarkani. A Multi-Objective Evolutionary Approach Towards Automated Online Controlled Experiments, Journal of Systems & Software, 2023.
- Wu, Jie JW, Thomas A. Mazzuchi, Shahram Sarkani. Comparison of multi-criteria decision-making methods for online controlled experiments in a launch decision-making framework, Information and Software Technology, 2023.
- Wu, Jie, Changhu Wang, Liqing Zhang, Yong Rui. Offline Sketch Parsing via Shapeness Estimation, IJCAI 2015. (M.S. Thesis)
- Wu, Jie, Changhu Wang, Liqing Zhang, Yong Rui. Sketch Recognition with Natural Correction and Editing, AAAI 2014. (M.S. Thesis)
- Wu, Jie, Changhu Wang, Liqing Zhang, Yong Rui. Sketch Recognition with Natural Correction and Editing, ACM MM 2014 (demo). (M.S. Thesis)
- **Wu, Jie** and Liqing Zhang. Gestalt Saliency: Salient Region Detection Based on Gestalt Principles, ICIP 2013. (B.S. Thesis, Top 1% Excellent Undergraduate Thesis Award at SJTU)
- Wu, Jie, Yi Liu, Ji-Rong Wen. Numeric Query Ranking Approach, WWW 2013 (poster).
- Wu, Jie, Li-Chen Shi, Bao-Liang Lu. Removing unrelated features based on linear dynamical system for motor-imagery-based brain-computer interface, ICONIP 2011.

#### Patents:

- Jonathan Brody, Donald Giovannini, Edward Koai, **Jie Wu**, Lin Zhong. "Additive Friend Suggestion for account security", United States Patent No. US 11,171,972 B1 (Granted)
- Carine Ramses Iskander, **Jie Wu**, Ian William Mikutel, Sarah Elizabeth Sykes, David Glen Garber. "Intuitive Selection of a Digital Stroke Grouping", United States Patent No. US 9,940,513 B2 (Granted)

# **HONORS**

"Engineer of the Month" (two-time winner) in the Friending team, for the contributions in Candidate Generation, Data, Privacy & Security of the Friending system. Jan 2022

**Letter from CEO** in recognition of the new friend suggestion generation model, Snap Inc. Jun 2019 National Scholarship. (Highest-level scholarship from the Chinese government). Oct 2014 Excellent Master Academic Scholarship (1st class), SJTU. Nov 2013

Intel Fellowship. Sep 2013
Excellent Undergraduate Thesis at SJTU (Top 1%). (38 out of nearly 4000 theses) Jun 2012
Microsoft Fellowship for Undergraduates. (30 among universities in China) Aug 2011
First Class Price, National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces (NOIP), Shanghai, Oct 2007

# REFERENCES

Thomas A. Mazzuchi, Professor,

Dept. of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering, School of Engineering & Applied Science(SEAS), Dept. of Decision Sciences, School of Business, George Washington University

mazzu@gwu.edu

Shahram Sarkani, Professor,
Dept. of Engineering Management and Systems Engineering,
George Washington University
sarkani@gwu.edu

Liqing Zhang, Professor and Chair, Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering, Shanghai Jiao Tong University <a href="mailto:zhang-lq@cs.sjtu.edu.cn">zhang-lq@cs.sjtu.edu.cn</a>

Yong Yu, Professor, Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering, Shanghai Jiao Tong University yyu@apex.sjtu.edu.cn

Ji-Rong Wen, Professor and Executive Dean, Gaoling School of Artificial Intelligence, Renmin University of China (RUC) jrwen@ruc.edu.cn

Yong Rui, Ph.D., Fellow of ACM, IEEE, AAAS, IAPR, SPIE, Chief Technology Officer, Senior Vice President at Lenovo Research, yongrui@lenovo.com

Jun Yu, Ph.D., Senior Manager at Snap Inc., Adjunct Professor, University of Washington, yujunnokia@gmail.com, https://zariable.github.io/

Changhu Wang, Ph.D., Head of Vision Technology at ByteDance, changhu.wang@outlook.com, https://changhu.wang/